VOL. 4, NO. 1, JANUARY 1966 AIAA JOURNAL 19
Compressible Turbulent Boundary Layer with Pressure
Gradient and Heat Transfer
a =
C f =
Cp =
g =
h =
H =
Hi =
Htr =
A:
L
M
N
Nu
p
q
R
T
u
UT
U
v
x
X
y
F
7
A
PHILIP K. SASMAN* AND ROBERT J.
Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn, Freeport, N. Y.
The compressible turbulent boundary layer is expressed in terms of the momentum integral
and moment-of-momentum integral equations for arbitrary pressure gradient. Upon simpli-
fication of this equation set with a Mager-type transformation, the two coupled differential
equations are solved simultaneously to provide boundary-layer momentum thickness, dis-
placement thickness, skin-friction coefficient, and related quantities as a function of the body
surface coordinate. The analysis includes surface heat-transfer effects. Results of the
analysis are presented for adiabatic, non-adiabatic, two-dimensional, and axisymmetric flow-
fields in a Mach number range between 2 and 8. Flows with favorable and adverse pressure
gradients are also examined. The present analysis is compared with available experimental
and theoretical results. The analysis is found to yield satisfactory results for flows with and
without heat transfer. In addition, for flows in the pressure of large adverse pressure gradients
in which the boundary layer is known to be well-behaved, spurious separation is not indi-
cated; instead, rather good agreement with available experimental data is observed.
Nomenclature
speed of sound
local skin-friction coefficient
coefficient of specific heat at constant pressure
normalized enthalpy, h/ho
enthalpy
form factor, d*/e
transformed plane form factor for adiabatic flow
transformed plane form factor for nonadiabatic flow,
A*/e0, 1 for 2-dimensional and axisymmetric flow, respectively
coefficient of thermal conductivity
reference length, 1 in.
Mach number
exponent of power law profile, (y/8)N, for the physical
plane
exponent of power law profile, (F/A)^*, for the trans-
formed plane
Nusselt number, qwCp0L/kQ(ho ù hw)
pressure
local heat-transfer rate
radius of axisymmetric body
temperature
longitudinal velocity
friction velocity, (rw/p)112
transformed longitudinal velocity
normal velocity
coordinate along body surface
transformed coordinate along body surface
normal coordinate
transformed normal coordinate
ratio of specific heats
transformed boundary-layer thickness
/╗ 8 / pu \displacement thickness, I ( 1 ù ùù J dyJO \ PeUe/
/òA IV U \
= transformed displacement thickness, I ( 1 ù ù ) +
dy,-, ò i C5 pu /ä u\6 = momentum thickness, I ùù I 1 ù ù )__________ J 0 PeUe \ Ue/
Received December 8, 1964; revision received September 13,
1965. This research was sponsored by the Aerospace Research
Laboratories, Office of Aerospace Research, U. S. Air Force,
Contract AF 33(657)-8286 under the technical cognizance of
Lieutenant A. J. Wennerstrom.
* Research Assistant.
t Associate Professor of Aerospace Engineering. Member
AIAA.
e
M
v
P
= transformed momentum thickness, I ù ( 1 ù ù ) dYJo Ue\ Ue/
= viscosity coefficient
= kinematic viscosity coefficient,
= mass density
= Prandtl number, Cp^/k
= shearing stress
= stream function
= transformed stream function
Subscripts
e = local external flow conditions
s = local stagnation conditions
w = wall or surface conditions
o = freestream stagnation conditions
Superscripts
(~~) = evaluated at reference conditions, Eq. (9)
I. Introduction
THE turbulent boundary layer has long been the subject
of investigation in fluid mechanics. In recent years the
understanding of detailed phenomena relating thereto has
been advanced significantly with concepts such as the law of
the wall and the law of the wake. However, despite these
new techniques, a general treatment of the compressible tur-
bulent boundary layer employing these methods has yet to be
accomplished.
From a pragmatic point of view, it is highly desirable to
couch the solution to the forementioned problem only in
terms of known variables of body geometry and the associated
inviscid flowfield conditions, rather than to appeal to pa-
rameters, such as the velocity defect, which have a funda-
mental importance in turbulent boundary-layer analysis.
Indeed, many investigators, motivated on grounds of prac-
ticality and attracted by the apparent conceptual simplicity,
have expressed their analyses and results of turbulent bound-
ary-layer behavior in terms of the boundary-layer form factor
(H) and momentum thickness (8). It should be observed,
however, that the boundary-layer form factor can be regarded
as something less than an ideal parameter for turbulent
boundary-layer analysis, since it is generally an unestablished
function of pressure distribution and skin friction.1 None-
theless, withstanding such apparent shortcomings, in the
past a significant amount of work has been accomplished with
the aid of the form factor parameter. For incompressible
flows, for example, Von Doenhoff and Tetervin2 used the
Downloaded by Imperial College London - Access Management on May 17, 2026 | http://arc.aiaa.org | DOI: 10.2514/3.3378 

20 P. K. SASMAN AND R. J. CRESCI AIAA JOURNAL
momentum equation together with an empirical auxiliary
equation to calculate boundary-layer form factor distribution.
More recently, Tetervin and Lin3 systematically expressed
the boundary-layer momentum, moment-of-momentum, and
energy integral equations using the form factor concept and
applied these results with reasonable success in the prediction
of turbulent separation on subsonic airfoils. Maskell4 has
also extended this process of turbulent boundary-layer analysis
by describing the variation of H with x by a series of empirical
functions that conveniently uncouple the variation of H from
the momentum integral equation.
For turbulent boundary layers in compressible flow,
Reshotko and Tucker5 again used the momentum and
moment-of-momentum integral equations in terms of the form
factor and the momentum thickness. The Stewartson trans-
formation was used together with the results of Maskell to
express the equations in an incompressible form and to un-
couple the two governing equations. This analysis resulted
in equations that should tentatively describe turbulent bound-
ary layers in compressible flow with heat transfer. The
Reshotko-Tucker analysis, which has enjoyed success for
favorable and mild adverse pressure gradient, however,
possesses some shortcomings when applied to flows with large
adverse gradients. One of the more serious of these is an in-
dicated boundary-layer separation in regions where the actual
boundary layer is reasonably well-behaved. In particular, the
unsatisfactory behavior of the analysis, when applied to a
flat plate followed by a curved compression surface, has been
demonstrated by McLafferty and Barber.6 Reference 6 has
also presented an empirical method of analysis which pro-
vides reasonable agreement with their experimental results.
The analysis presented herein attempts to eliminate some
shortcomings of the earlier methods by incorporating more
recently available results of turbulent boundary-layer
analyses. This analysis is similar, in some respects, to the
work of Ref. 5; the boundary-layer momentum integral
equation is used in conjunction with the moment-of-momen-
tum equation. The wall shearing stress is given by the Lud-
wieg-Tillmann7 formulation. However, unlike previous in-
vestigations no attempt is made to uncouple the momentum
and moment-of-momentum integral equations. Instead, the
set of two differential equations is solved simultaneously after
introduction of normalized boundary-layer shearing stress
distributions. The shear distributions are established from
numerical results of equilibrium turbulent boundary-layer
analysis.
II. Development of Analysis
A. Basic Equations
For steady, compressible turbulent flow the Prandtl
boundary-layer equations, in which flow variables appear as
time-averaged quantities, are expressible by
d(pu)/dx + d(pv)/dy + j(pu/R)(dR/dx) = 0 (1)
and
pu(bu/~bx} + pv(du/by) = ù (dp/dx) + brfdy (2)
To simplify the final boundary-layer integral equations a
Mager-type8 transformation is employed, which is of the form
X = CXb(x)dxJ o
and
where
Y = c(x) ù dyPo
(3)
(4)
and where X and Y represent the transformed coordinates.
Consistent with the transformation in which ^ = \f/, it is
useful to observe that
u = cU H = [1 + (7 - l)Me*/2]Htr + (7 -
and
5* = (0 + L
It may be recalled that the functional dependence of b (x)
and c(x) for the transformation of form (3) and (4) remains
arbitrary until several additional conditions are imposed
beyond the initial requirement that the Jacobian of the trans-
formation be nonvanishing, and likewise that requirements
are generally dictated such that the resulting equations are
simplified if not made completely analogous to the incom-
pressible flow equations. In this context it may be observed
that the foregoing explicit transformation differs slightly from
that used by Mager in that he postulates that the apparent
turbulent shear stress associated with an elemental mass re-
main invariant under transformation; this postulate has been
subject to question, as commented on, for example, by Coles.9
The transformed momentum integral equation (5) follows
from the governing equations (1) and (2) after applying the
preceding transformation.
6 dR
R dX T
T_ \
Tj p.Ut (5)
where
and
In a manner similar to Ref, 5, the accompanying moment-
of-momentum integral equation corresponding to Eq. (5) is
obtained. Although the general derivation procedure is given
in Ref. 5 for completeness, the mechanics of the development
shall be restated here briefly; the differential form of Eq. (5)
is multiplied by F, and the result integrated with respect to Y
from F = 0 to Y = A. To aid in the reduction of the resulting
equation to manageable form, the results of Tetervin and Lin3
are utilized. It may be observed that the resulting Eq. (6) is
ostensibly the same as that of Ref. 5, except for the modifica-
tion of the transformation employed:
dX
J. dU_e
Ue dx
1 +
- I)' X
1)02
X
T\T\p.U.*
It - I) (Hi
e x
B. Boundary-Layer Shear Relationships
The Ludwieg-Tillman skin-friction relation for incompressi-
ble turbulent flow was selected for use in the analysis. For,
in addition to its convenient formulation, the expression for
Downloaded by Imperial College London - Access Management on May 17, 2026 | http://arc.aiaa.org | DOI: 10.2514/3.3378 

JANUARY 1966 TURBULENT BOUNDARY LAYER 21
Cf is valid over a wide range of pressure gradients as various
authors have noted.1 The formulation for incompressible
flow from Ref. 7 is given by
o o.ooi < cf/2 * 0.002
ù ~ Aù Tw/z (7)
The corresponding skin-friction coefficient for compressible
flow is obtained upon application of the reference enthalpy
concept. As noted by Tetervin,10 the reference enthalpy
method is quite easily applied to a C/ law with a Ree de-
pendence without resorting to a flat-plate momentum equa-
tion when it is recognized that 6 likewise contains a base
density. Indeed, if a flat-plate equation were used, the
reference method might appear restricted to zero pressure
gradient flows.
Therefore, adapting Eq. (7) for compressible flow
rw/pue2 = O.^Se-^M^A)"0'268
And since p/pe = Te/T
Tw/peu? = 0.l23e-1^^i(ueO/p)-░-2G8(Te/T)1^ (8)
where (~~) refers to conditions evaluated at the reference tem-
perature given by Eckert,11
T/To = 0.5TW/T0 + 0.220-1/3 + (0.5 - 0.220-1/3)(77e/770) (9)
Since 6 = (T0/Te)*Q and ue = (Te/TQ)u*UeioT 7 = 1.4, then
Cf/2 = Tw/peiie* = 0.123e-1-561^(C/e0Ao)-░-268 X
68 (10)
Evaluation of the normalized boundary-layer shear dis-
tribution arising in Eq. (6) is also required for the solution of
Eqs. (3) and (4). To this end, the results of equilibrium tur-
bulent boundary-layer analysis are incorporated. In par-
ticular, as shown by Libby et al.,12
)"'/ä'½.//.-where F ù ue/uT[(u/ue) ù 1] and 77 = y/d for an incom-
pressible flowfield. If a wide range of both adverse and
favorable equilibrium pressure distributions are considered,
then the shear integral may be expressed in the approximate
form
fJo *,- 0.011H, 2 (12)
where C/ is the appropriate skin-friction coefficient for the
incompressible flow. In this sense, care should be exercised
in relating C/ to the flowfield it is assumed to represent.
The functional dependence of
C1 T
JQ Tw
upon Hi as given by the preceding analysis is presented in
Fig. 1. Also shown is the shear distribution assumed in
Ref. 5; this has a much smaller range of validity due to,
among other reasons, the assumed functional dependence
only upon Hi. The available experimental results (cf. Refs.
13-15) are also included in Fig. 1. All the data have been
obtained for an incompressible flow, and in the majority of
cases adverse pressure gradients are present. As may be
noted, there exists an underabundance of detailed experi-
mental turbulent boundary-layer data even for the incom-
pressible case and essentially none for the compressible case.
C. Extension to Nonadiabatic Flow
For unity Prandtl number, the integrals
- l)dY and f * (g - l)YdYJQ
A 0.0005
m o.oooiO REF. (15)
╗ REF (13)
ò REF (14)
ùùùùREF(5)
0.001
0.0004
Fig. 1 Shear integral for incompressible turbulent
boundary layers.
arising in Eqs. (5) and (6) are equal to zero for adiabatic flow.
To evaluate these integrals for an arbitrary but constant sur-
face temperature, the Crocco relation is employed with a
power law assumption for the velocity profiles, assuming the
Prandtl and Lewis numbers are unity. Specifically, when
(hs - hw)/(h0 - hw) = u/ue =
then
and
U/U, = (F/A)N*
- l)dY = (13)
J/ (g - l)YdY = (gw - 1) ^f^t^.'ox 62 (14)
where
2(Ht -
i = 2Ni + 1
3)
It is interesting to note that a Mager-type transformation
causes increased distortion of the velocity profiles with increas-
ing external Mach number. As noted in Ref. 16, if Ni is as-
sumed constant as in a typical power law velocity profile,
then the physical profile parameter N will vary with the nor-
mal coordinate y.
Although there is some question concerning the applicability
of the Crocco relation for flows with heat transfer and pres-
sure gradient, this was utilized in the present analysis in place
of solving the energy integral equation directly. A more in-
volved approach would be to solve the energy integral equa-
tion simultaneously with the momentum and moment-of-
momentum integral equations. This has been done in pre-
vious analyses (e.g., Ref. 22), and the results, in general, indi-
cated that the additional complexity did not improve the
solution over that obtained by utilizing the Crocco relation.
As a result, it is felt that the enthalpy integral evaluation of
Eqs. (13) and (14) should be sufficiently accurate for the range
of validity of the analysis.
Downloaded by Imperial College London - Access Management on May 17, 2026 | http://arc.aiaa.org | DOI: 10.2514/3.3378 

22 P. K. SASMAN AND R. J. CRESCI AIAA JOURNAL
ùùù PRESENT ANALYSIS
ùùùù RESHOTKO-TUCKER {REF5)
:ùùùù FPRE(REF.H)
VAN DRIEST (REF 17)
===fP0-2N6psf
!ùù T0=6!0░R
, M.-7.0 4
;=|>P0½2.45xlOpsf
VI800-R
Fig. 2 Skin-friction variation on an adiabatic flat plate
(*. = 1-0).
The relation between the actual form factor (H) and the in-
compressible form factor (Hi) is, therefore, given by
H = thffi[l + (7 - 1)^7/2] + (7 - l)M.*/2 (15)
Incorporating the results of the preceding sections, the
momentum integral equation (5) may be written
dS/dX + (Q/U.)(dU./dX)[2 + gwHi] + j(Q/K)(dR/dX) =
O.me-i-^M^eAo) -░'Ö(T,/T0) (/I/Mo)0-268 (16)
and the moment-of-momentum equation (6) may be written
dX We d.
[l + fa. - 1) (Hi + I) (Hi +
~HiTW (Hi + 1)
e
In the past, investigators4'5 have uncoupled the momentum
equation from the preceding equation set using semiempirical
approximations. With the present capability of computing
machines, and in order to maintain the coupling effect of Hi
and 6, it was deemed highly desirable to retain the momen-
tum equation in the form of Eq. (16) and to solve this numeri-
cally in conjunction with Eq. (17).
It may be seen that both Eqs. (16) and (17) of the equation
set appear to have singularities at 6 = 0. It can be observed
that Eq. (17) has a nonremovable singularity in contrast to
Eq. (16), which may be rewritten in the form
1.268-
j(f/R)(dR/dX) =
where
(f/Ue)(dUe/dX)[l
(18)
Equations (17) and (18) may also be expressed in the form
df/dx = L2Q8{(-f/Me)(dM,/dx)[(l + gjli) -
(JV/R)(dR/dx) + A]} (19)
and
dx - 2Me dx [Hi(Hi +
i - 1)] X
[l + (Qw - 1)
A
(ff,+ !)(#< +3) J /
0.011 (Hi + I) (Hi - I)2 2
/ =
where
and
,4. =
Hence, upon specification of a body shape and the ac-
companying external flowfield, simultaneous solution of the
preceding differential equations yield H(x) and B(x) for the
boundary layer in question. Typical initial conditions for
these equations are discussed in the numerical examples that
follow.
III. Comparison of Analysis with Theoretical
and Experimental Results
Application of the analysis and comparison with other
theoretical results is afforded by several examples given below.
PRESENT ANALYSIS
ùùù RESHOTKO-TUCKER (REF. 5)
20
20
Fig. 3 Nusselt number distribution on a flat plate (gw 
0.3).
Fig. 4 Variation of integral thicknesses on a flat plate
Gr½, - 1.0).
Downloaded by Imperial College London - Access Management on May 17, 2026 | http://arc.aiaa.org | DOI: 10.2514/3.3378 

JANUARY 1966 TURBULENT BOUNDARY LAYER 23
The numerical results are obtained by a Runga-Kutta inte-
gration technique programed on a Bendix G-15 digital com-
puter. Reference quantities are determined by Eckert's
reference enthalpy formulation for Prandtl number equal to
0.72; viscosity ratios are determined by the Sutherland
formula.
A. Flow over Flat Plates
Adiabatic and nonadiabatic flat-plate flows for Mach
numbers of 3 and 7 are examined in Figs. 2-5. Inasmuch as
one of the integral equations is singular at a; = 0, Hi was set
equal to 1.3 in the vicinity of the leading edge. At a small
distance downstream of the leading edge both equations were
solved simultaneously, yielding rapid convergence to the
actual value of Hi.
For gw = 1, Fig. 2 shows the variation of skin friction with
Rex obtained from different analyses. For comparison, the
methods of Reshotko-Tucker,5 van Driest,17 and the flat-plate
reference enthalpy method18 (FPRE) are also presented. The
van Driest formulation using the Prandtl mixing length
hypothesis is employed. All of the analyses shown are in
close agreement at low external Mach numbers but tend to
diverge as the Mach number increases.
For gw = 0.3, Fig. 3 shows the Nusselt number dependence
on Rex. Here, as in the remainder of the examples, use is
made of Reynolds7 analogy for <r = 0.72. Again, it is noted
that generally close agreement is obtained for all analyses.
The momentum and displacement thickness for the various
flat plates considered are given in Figs. 4 and 5. Dependence
of 0 and 5* on Rex are compared with the predictions of
Ref. 5 under the same flow conditions. It is noted that as ex-
ternal Mach numbers increase, the variation in 5* and 6 be-
tween the results of Ref. 5 and the present analysis becomes
more pronounced, although qualitatively the behavior of the
boundary-layer thicknesses is similar.
B. Axisymmetric Flow with Mild Adverse Pressure
Gradient
Zakkay and Callahan19 obtained, among others, experi-
mental heat-transfer data over a cone-cylinder-flare con-
figuration shown schematically in Fig. 6. A mild adverse
Rex x 106
Fig. 5 Variation of integral thicknesses on a flat plate
(#½, = 0.3).
E: 5.5" ___-^i
I ä3.875"
i
| ùùùùùùù 17.375" ùùùùùùùù -
ùùù 12.000" ùùùùù -
T5.950"
1
Me
l░0^- 0.6
O EXPER.DATA(REF.I9)
ùùù PRESENT ANALYSIS
ùùù FPRE (REF. 18)
1.0 1.4 1.8
X(FT)
Fig. 6 Mach number and Nusselt number distributions
on axisymmetric configuration.19
pressure gradient is present on the aft portion of the model as
indicated by the resulting Mach number distribution given in
Fig. 6.
The present analysis is applied to the configuration of Ref.
19 using the test condition corresponding to the largest extent
of fully turbulent flow achieved in the test series. These
conditions are presented in Fig. 6. The analysis is initiated in
the laminar-transitional region of the body, using an initial
value of momentum thickness computed from laminar theory
in Ref. 19. Although the starting value of Hi equal to 1.9 is
that associated with a laminar boundary layer, the solution
rapidly converges to the fully developed turbulent boundary-
layer solution ; this is readily seen in the plot of Nusselt num-
ber vs surface distance (Fig. 6). The heat transfer predicted
by the present analysis rapidly converges to values expected
from a fully turbulent boundary-layer flow, as indicated by
the FPRE method. It is seen that on the aft portion of the
body, where the flow is fully turbulent, good agreement is ob-
tained between experimental data and the present analysis.
It is also significant that the behavior of the solution indicates
that the results are relatively insensitive to the starting values
used in the analysis.
Here, Reynolds analogy has again been employed in the
form
Nu = (21)
where 0-1/3 is the empirical correction for nonunity Prandtl
number, and where the adiabatic wall enthalpy (haw) is de-
fined in terms of the recovery factor
(kaw - he) /(ho ~ he) = O-1/3
Equation (21) has been applied in this case to the pressure-
gradient flow of Ref. 19 to provide a means of comparison.
It was found, as in Ref. 22, that the accuracy of Nu prediction
did not increase significantly for calculations made by extend-
ing Reynolds analogy to include pressure gradient terms.
C. Flows with Strong Adverse Pressure Gradient
The adiabatic flows of Ref. 6 are of particular interest for
they contain large adverse pressure gradients, as can be seen
Downloaded by Imperial College London - Access Management on May 17, 2026 | http://arc.aiaa.org | DOI: 10.2514/3.3378 

24 P. K. SASMAN AND R. J. CRESCI AIAA JOURNAL
4.12"
INJECTIONPLENUM
1.6
3.2
3.0
2.4
2.2
2.0
1.8
x=0 T0=6IO░R
P0=2II6 psf
½½
0.4
^
A
r=^L
| 0 EXPER. D
f ùùù PRESE
/I ùùù RESHC
/ùj ùùùùùùùùù
A /_ ù ù -"""Tr"^
/
ATA, FLOW I, REF 6
\TA.FLOWH, REF 6
:NT ANALYSIS
)TKO- TUCKER (REF 5)
A
I
X
CD
0.10 020 0.30
0.05 0.10 0.15 0.20 0.25 0.30
X(FT)
X (FT)
b) MOMENTUM THICKNESS
Fig. 7 Two-dimensional model configuration and Mach
number distribution.6
from Fig. 7. The two flowfields shown, denoted in the present
figures by flow I and II, respectively, were obtained by com-
pressing an initially uniform Mach 3 flow over a flat plate
by insertion of a compression surface. The geometry of the
two-dimensional tunnel model is also shown in Fig. 7. To
vary the boundary-layer thickness at x = 0, a small amount
of air was injected into the boundary layer upstream of the
surface under consideration. Additional details can be found
in Ref. 6.
Employing the experimentally determined external flow-
fields and initial conditions cited by this reference, the result-
Fig. 9 Variation of boundary-layer thicknesses on two-
dimensional model.
ing variations of Hi and 0 and consequently 0, d*, and C//2
are obtained by the present analysis. The skin friction and
boundary-layer thicknesses are presented in Figs. 8 and 9,
along with the experimental data for flow I and II. Ex-
amination of Figs. 9a and 9b reveals good agreement between
the analysis and the experimentally measured values of 5*
and 8. Again, for purposes of comparison with other methods,
results of the Reshotko-Tucker analysis are also included.
Although no direct measurement of C/ was made in Ref. 6, by
inspection of the C//2 vs x curves in Fig. 8, it is seen that the
present analysis yields a variation in skin-friction coefficient
1:0
0.8
0.6
0.4
0.2
ùùùùù PRESENT ANALYSIS
ùùùùù RESHOTKO - TUCKER (REF. 5)
I \rt
6.0
4.0
2.0
n
0 EXPER. DATA, FLOWI, REF. 21
A EXPER. DATA, FLOWI, REF. 21
-^
^ ùù - ùù ùùù
_
a) MACH NUMBER
0 O.I 0.2 0.3
X (FT)
Fig. 8 Variation of skin-friction coefficient on two-di-
mensional model.
4.0 8.0 12.0
X (FT)
c) MOMENTUM THICKNESS
Fig. 10 Variation of Mach number and boundary-layer
thicknesses on a nozzle.20
Downloaded by Imperial College London - Access Management on May 17, 2026 | http://arc.aiaa.org | DOI: 10.2514/3.3378 

JANUARY, 1966 TURBULENT BOUNDARY LAYER 25
O EXPER. DATA , REF. 21
ùùù PRESENT ANALYSIS
ùùù ANALYSIS OF REF 21
Fig. 11 Variation of skin friction and momentum thick-
ness on axisymmetric configuration.21
that does not approach zero and, therefore, is consistent with
the experimental observation that separation did not occur
for this flow.
D. Flows with Favorable Pressure Gradient
Several favorable and favorable-adverse pressure gradient
flows were also considered. The first case in point is repre-
sented by data from two California Institute of Technology
Jet Propulsion Laboratory supersonic nozzles, as shown in
Fig. 10. Calculations were initiated at the nozzle throats
using initial 0 values listed in Ref. 20. It may be seen that
both <5* and 6 agree closely with the experimental points ob-
tained by Dayman20 for the Mach 5 and the Mach 2 adiabatic
nozzles.
Secondly, Mach 2 flow past an axisymmetric waisted body
of Ref. 21 is examined (Fig. 11). Calculation was initiated in
the boundary-layer transition region. Again, it may be ob-
served that 6 is in good agreement with data points, as is
Cf/2, which falls within the range of experimental error stated
in Ref. 21. Also shown are the analysis curves of this ref-
erence. The analysis curves were obtained by approximating
the very difficult task of simultaneous integration of both
momentum and energy integral equations through preliminary
correlations of the adiabatic data to be analyzed subsequently.
Such an analysis, in which direct consideration is given to the
energy equation, might indeed be promising if the initial dif-
ficulties of this approach can be transcended. As shown in
Ref. 21, extension of such an approach to other than adiabatic
flows within a small Mach number range appears to be
reasonably difficult.
IV. Conclusions
The results of the present analysis indicate that the simul-
taneous solution of the boundary-layer integral equations,
without attempting to uncouple the same, may indeed be a
possible method for treatment of the general compressible
turbulent boundary layer. The present method yields skin-
friction coefficients and other boundary-layer parameters in
close agreement with experimental and theoretical results over
a wide range of zero, favorable, and adverse pressure-gradient
flows. Favorable results for nonadiabatic flows with zero
and mild pressure gradients are also obtained.
In addition, it was found that this method of analysis did
not give spurious indication of separation in the presence of
large adverse pressure gradients, but yielded boundary-layer
parameters in good agreement with experimentally obtained
data.
References
1 Clauser, F., "The turbulent boundary layer," Advances in
Applied Mechanics (Academic Press Inc., New York, 1956), Vol.
IV.
2Von Doenhoff, A. E. and Tetervin, N., "Determination of
general relations for the behavior of turbulent boundary layers,"
NACA Rept, 772 (1943).
3 Tetervin, N. and Lin, C. C., "A general integral form of the
boundary-layer equation for incompressible flow with an ap-
plication to the calculation of the separation point of turbulent
boundary layers," NACA Kept. 1046 (1951).
4 Maskell, E. C., "Approximate calculation of the turbulent
boundary layer in two-dimensional incompressible flow," British
Royal Aircraft Establishment Rept. Aero 2443 (1951).
5 Reshotko, E. and Tucker, M., "Approximate calculation of
the compressible turbulent boundary layer with heat transfer and
arbitrary pressure gradient," NACA TN 4154 (1957).
6 McLafferty, G. H. and Barber, R. E., "The effect of adverse
pressure gradients on the characteristics of turbulent boundary
layers in supersonic streams," J. Aerospace Sci. 29, 1-18 (1962).
7 Ludwieg, H. and Tillmann, W., "Investigations of the wall
shearing-stress in turbulent boundary layers," NACA TN 1285
(1950).
8 Mager, A., Transformation of the compressible turbulent
boundary layer," J. Aerospace Sci. 25, 305-311 (1958).
9 Coles, D. E., The turbulent boundary layer in a compressible
fluid," Phys. Fluids 7, 1403-1423 (September 1964).
10 Tetervin, N., "The application of the reference-enthalpy
method to friction formulas," J. Aerospace Sci. 29, 493 (1962).
11 Eckert, E. R. G., "Engineering relations for friction and heat
transfer to surfaces in high velocity flow," J. Aeronaut. Sci. 22,
585-586(1955).
12 Libby, P. A., Baronti, P. O., and Napolitano, P., "Study of
the incompressible turbulent boundary layer with pressure
gradient," AIAA J. 2, 445-452 (1964).
13 Sandborn, V. A. and Slogan, R. J., "Study of the momentum
distribution of turbulent boundary layers in adverse pressure
gradients," NACA TN 3264 (1955).
14 Newman, M. A., "Some contributions to the study of the
turbulent boundary-layer near separation," Australian Aero-
nautical Research Consultative Committee, Rept. ACA-53
(1951).
15 Schubauer, G. B. and Klebanoff, P. S., "Investigation of
separation of the turbulent boundary layer," NACA TN 2133
(1950).
16 Reshotko, E. and Tucker, M., "Effect of a discontinuity on
turbulent boundary-layer thickness parameters with application
to shock-induced separation," NACA TN 3454 (1955).
17 van Driest, E. R., "The problem of aerodynamic heating,"
Aeronaut. Eng. Rev. 15, 26-41 (October 1956).
18 Cresci, 11. J., MacKenzie, D. A., and Libby, P. A., "An in-
vestigation of laminar, transitional, and turbulent heat transfer
on blunt-nosed bodies in hypersonic flow," J. Aerospace Sci. 27,
401-414(1960).
19 Zakkay, V. and Callahan, C. J., "Laminar, transitional and
turbulent heat transfer to a cone-cylinder-flare body at Mach
8.0," J. Aerospace Sci. 29,1403-1420 (1962).
20 Dayman, B., "Comparison of calculated with measured
boundary-layer thicknesses on the curved walls of the JPL 20 inch
supersonic wind tunnel two-dimensional nozzle," California Insti-
tute of Technology Jet Propulsion Laboratory TR 32-349 (March
1963).
21 Winter, K. G., Smith, K. G., and Rotta J. C., "Turbulent
boundary-layer studies on a waisted body of revolution in sub-
sonic and supersonic flow,' AGARDograph 97, Pt. II (May
1965).
22 Libby, P. A. and Cresci, R. J., "Evaluation of several hyper-
sonic turbulent heat transfer analyses by comparison with experi-
mental data," Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn Aerospace Lab.
PIBAL 387, Wright Air Development Center WADC TN 57-72
(July 1957).
Downloaded by Imperial College London - Access Management on May 17, 2026 | http://arc.aiaa.org | DOI: 10.2514/3.3378 

